Finding Aid for Institute for the Humanities (University of Michigan) Records 1988-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute for the Humanities (University of Michigan) records 1988-2001
University of Michigan. Institute for the Humanities.
The Institute for the Humanities, founded in 1987, was developed in response to a recognized need for renewed dialogue across disciplines. Originally oriented around the humanities and the arts, the center soon evolved into a widely recognized venue for international scholarship. The records are largely comprised of video and sound cassettes documenting a diverse range of events.
0134 Bimu; C6; 2
5 linear feet in 11 boxes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the Institute for the Humanities in 1999. Donor no. 8595
The collection, while open for research, includes restricted files. These files have been removed to Box 11.
Since World War II there has been an evolution toward a division of knowledge into discrete fields, resulting in ever narrowing areas of scholarly interest and focus. The Institute for the Humanities at the University of Michigan was founded in 1987 partly in response to a recognized need for renewed dialogue across the disciplines. However, it was also developed because there was already evidence of increased intellectual overlap between and among fields in the humanities: literary scholars using the perspectives of anthropology to study the origins of myth; musicologists and art historians using economic history to explain how patronage affected stylistic development; classicists combining the methods of many disciplines in the quest for knowledge of the ancient world. James A. Winn, who was the center's first director, spoke to the synergistic nature of the Institute's mission: "We do not oppose specialization. Instead, we attempt to transcend it by challenging the expert researcher and the innovative theorist to think about their findings on a larger level, as they relate to other investigations in other disciplines, and to excel in original and innovative ways."
The first executive committee, which was formed to assist an appointed director on policy and advise in the selection of internal and visiting fellows and associates, included faculty members from law, romance languages, Japanese studies, music, classics, and history. They, along with interim director John Knott, worked to set the stage for an exemplary interdisciplinary innovation in the humanities and the arts. After several years of planning, the Institute for the Humanities moved into a newly renovated suite of rooms in the Horace H. Rackham Building in September 1987.
While the earliest years primarily focused on building the program, raising an endowment, and increasing the number of fellows, the Institute quickly became a widely recognized center for international scholarship. Under Winn's directorship, the Institute, in just a few years, realized every guiding principle originally envisioned and defined: encourage interdisciplinary discourse and activity; promote the innovative and controversial; build bridges between the creative and performing arts and the analytical work done by humanists; develop an undergraduate dimension; and make findings available to a broad audience. Winn promoted broad, collaborative, integrative teaching in the humanities. Unlike programs elsewhere, the UM initiative, from the start, included a vital teaching component. Fellows developed new pedagogical models for instruction, moved across departmental boundaries, and welcomed students of all levels in their courses.
Institute programs continued to expand and develop. In addition to sponsored courses and mini-courses, key conferences and forums punctuated each term. (Until 1999, conference papers and other program components were oriented around an annual theme.) The Institute's commitment to fostering new connections between the settings in which scholars express themselves and the settings in which artists express themselves resulted in numerous performances each year in theatre, dance and music. Events were framed by panel discussions, brownbag lunches, and lectures.
In 1990, the Institute incorporated into the dialogue the examination of intersections between scientific and humanistic thought. In that year, undergraduate science majors participated in discussions ranging from medical ethics and the behavioral differences among primates, to the implications of technological change for humanists. In 1991, the center innovatively reached out to alumni. A Humanities Camp was instituted. Alumni were invited to a spring weekend of seminars, field trips, lectures and informal gatherings - all oriented around the humanities and designed to showcase some of the best faculty and experiences available at the University of Michigan.
In 1997, as the Institute entered its tenth year, Tom Trautmann, a former fellow, became its second director. In a letter published in the 1996-1997 annual report, Trautmann reaffirmed the center's guiding purpose: "I believe strongly in the Institute's central mission of supporting a community of scholars, both faculty and students, engaged in the creation of knowledge in the humanities."
Directors of the Institute for the Humanities
1987-1988 John R. Knott, Interim Director
1988-1996 James A. Winn, Director
1990-1991 Domna C. Stanton, Acting Director
1996-1997 Diane Kirkpatrick, Interim Director
1997- Tom Trautmann, Director
Institute for the Humanities Annual Themes
1999-2000 Open to Interdisciplinary Proposals
1998-1999 Form and Pattern
1997-1998 Narrative
1996-1997 Images and the Imaginary
1995-1996 Emotion
1994-1995 Work and Play
1993-1994 The Geography of Identity
1992-1993 Utopian Visions
1991-1992 Authority of the Past
1990-1991 Histories of Sexuality
1989-1990 Economies of Art
1988-1989 Translation: Cultural Confrontation and Transformation
1987-1988 Theatre and Society
There are two series in the Institute for the Humanities record group: Administrative Records and Audio-Visual Material. The records, largely comprised of videotapes and cassette tapes, provide dynamic evidence of the steady growth and refinement of an initiative that greatly enriched teaching and scholarship in the humanities at the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Intellectual life.; Scholars--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Humanities--Study and teaching.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Intellectual life.; Scholars--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Humanities--Study and teaching.; Music.; Utopias.; Emotions.; Memory.; Theater.; Identity.; Art--Philosophy.; Symbolism in art.; Sex and history.; Play (Philosophy); Scholars--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scholars--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre/Form:
Videotapes.; Sound recordings.
- Administrative Records
  The Administrative Records series, while slight (ca. .5 linear ft.), is important because it is currently the only source of information in the record group that is text-based. The most significant documentation is in several folders of year-end reports prepared by Institute sponsored fellows; a folder of exit interview notes is also informative. The latter, a 1991-1992 project designed to evaluate expectations, events, and services was also geared toward gathering recommendations from fellows. The series also includes a folder of applications from students, ca. 1992-1996. Four additional application folders hold correspondence and accompanying material from undergraduates applying for the Program in the Sciences and Humanities.
  - Applications
    - Undergraduate
      - 1992-1996, 2 folders (Box 11)
        (RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2071 )
    - Program in the Sciences and Humanities
      - 1992-1993 (Box 11)
        (RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2068 )
      - 1994-1995 (Box 11)
        (RESTRICTED until Jan. 1, 2070 )
      - 1995-1996 (Box 11)
  - Exit Interviews 1992 (Box 1)
  - Program and budget 1988-2001 (Box 1)
  - Year-End Reports
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual series, consisting of rich and excellent documentation of lectures, speeches, conferences, and events, is arranged chronologically by year and then by two formats: VHS videotape and audio-cassette tape. Researchers should note that there might be overlap (that is, the same lecture or conference recorded and described in each format). Presenters, when known, are identified by field (discipline) and institution.
  The extent of the documentation varies from year to year. There is very little for 1987-1988 (Theatre and Society) and only the second semester is represented for 1988-1989 (Translation: Cultural Confrontation and Transformation). The years between 1989 and 1997 are well documented in recordings of conferences, forums, lectures, brown bags, and performances. Recent years, 1997-1998 and 1998-1999, contain only a few items.
  Researchers are reminded that printed material in the form of publications is described in a finding aid immediately following this one. A complete run of annual reports is a highly recommended source for further information, and for adding context to the audio-visual records. Here one can find, year-by-year, annual highlights, program schedules and notes, profiles of UM fellows and visiting fellows, and development activities.
  - Theater and Society 1987-1988
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Laurie Sears, History, University of Wisconsin. Lecture: "Theatre of the Eternal Return: Shadows of a Japanese Past" March 31, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Richard Schechner, Performance Studies, New York University. Lecture: "Masks and Shadows of Knowing" March 31, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Panel discussion: "wayang, the Marriage of Ajuna" April 2, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Translation: Cultural Confrontation and Transformation 1988-1989
    - Videotapes
      - Henry Louis Gates, Jr., W.E.B. DuBois Professor of Literature, Cornell University. Speech: [on Black American literature and the process of canon formation] January 25, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Anton Shammas, senior Visiting Fellow, Palestinian Israeli novelist. Reading: from Arabesques, January 26, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Donald Davidson, Philosophy, University of California at Berkeley. Lecture: "How Can You Tell If a Machine is Thinking?" March 16, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Sam Supalla, storyteller. Conference session: "Staged Hands: Sign Language Translation in the Theater" March 17-18, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Conference: "Translation: Cultural Confrontation and Transformation." April 1, 1988 (Box 2)
        (Participants: Anthony Pagden, History, Cambridge University; Dennis Tedlock, Program in Folklore, Mythology, and Film Studies, State University of New York at Buffalo; Anthony Appiah, Philosophy, Cornell; Peggy Kamuf, French, University of Southern California; A. K. Ramanujan, South Asian Languages and Civilizations and Committee on Social Thought, University of Chicago; Anton Shammas, Palestinian Israeli novelist)
      - Anthony Pagden, History, Cambridge University. "What's Wrong with Intelligent History?" April 12, 1988 (Box 2)
      - Richard Terdiman, French Literature and History of Consciousness, University of California at Santa Cruz. Lecture: "Something from Nowhere: History and Difference in Poststructuralist Theory" April 21, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Economies of Art 1989-1990
    - Videotapes
      - Conference: "Economies of Art Today: Policies and Problems." November 10, 1989, 2 videotapes
        - Martha Duffy, Senior Editor Time Magazine. Conference session: "Funding the Performing Arts in the 90s." Nicholas Delbanco, English, University of Michigan. Conference session: "The Writer's Trade." Roger L. Stevens, Founding Chairman, John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts. Conference session: "The Founding of the National Endowment for the Arts" (Box 2)
        - Peggy Cooper Cafritz, Chair, The Ellington Fund. Conference session: "Inequities in the Economies of Art." Robert Freeman, Director, Eastman School of Music, University of Rochester. Conference session: "The Economics of America's Orchestras in the Century Ahead." Rudolf Arnheim, Professor Emeritus, Psychology of Art, Harvard University. Conference session: "When Rembrandt Bent Down: Values Given and Values Invented" (Box 2)
      - Faith Ringgold, New York City textile artist. Brown Bag: "An Artist Dealing with the Art Establishment" November 14, 1989 (Box 2)
      - Margaret Miles, Historical Theology, Harvard Divinity School. Forum: "Signorelli's Resurrection of the Flesh" January 11, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Samuel Floyd, Jr. Lecture: Martin Luther King Birthday lecture, "The Role of Music in the Harlem Renaissance" January 22, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Conference: "Economies of Art: History and Theory" January 25-27, 1990, 6 videotapes
        - Panel: History and Theory (Box 2)
        - Tom Crow, History of Art, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Contemporary Art and the Market in Theory" (Box 2)
        - Biodun Jeyifo, English, Cornell University. Conference session: "Arrested Decolonization and the Discourse on Literary Value" (Box 2)
        - Ruth Behar, Anthropology, University of Michigan. Conference session: "Crossing the Border with a Mexican Woman's Life Story: Economies of Fieldwork and Textwork" (Box 2)
        - Cora Kaplan, English, Rutgers. Conference session: "Like Any Other Rebel Slave" (Box 2)
        - Gary Tomlinson, Music, University of Pennsylvania. Conference session: "Music, Magic, History, Value" (Box 2)
      - Samuel Floyd Jr., Center for Black Music Research, Columbia College of Chicago. Forum: "A Chicago Renaissance?" February 2, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Mikhail Shatrov, Soviet dramatist. Forum: "Drama in the Soviet Union" February 23, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Conference. "Economies of Art" January 25, 1990, 3 audiocassettes (Box 2)
      - Sally McConnell-Ginet, Modern Languages and Linguistics, Cornell University. Lecture: "Humpty-Dumpty meets Alice: The Sexual Politics of Word Meanings" January 30, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Nicola Petrov on Upcoming USSR Election, WUOM Interview February 14, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Histories of Sexuality 1990-1991
    - Videotapes
      - Mae Henderson, University of Illinois, Chicago. Lecture: "The Stories of O(Dessa)" September 14, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Thomas Laqueur, History, University of California at Berkeley. Forum: Making Sex: The Body and Gender from Greeks to Freud, October 19, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Conference: "Michel Foucault's History of Sexuality", November 2, 1990, 2 videotapes (Box 3)
        (Participants: Judith Butler, Arnold Davidson, Lesley Dean-Jones; Lynn Hunt; Abdul JanMohamed; Jim Miller)
      - Francoise Barret Duchrocq. Forum: "Conflicting Modes of Male and Female Behavior in 19th Century England" November 16, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Carol Armstrong, Art History, University of California at Berkeley. Forum: "A Feminine Practice: The Case of Julia Margaret Cameron" November 30, 1990 (Box 3)
      - Bekherjee Mukherjee. Forum: "An Immigration Tragedy" January 25, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Bill T. Jones / Arne Zane Dance Company: "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / Promised Land" January 26, 1991, 2 videotapes (Box 3)
      - Conference: "Constructed Body" February 15-16, 1991, 7 videotapes (Box 3)
        (Participants: Douglas Crimp, David Halperin, Stephen Heath, Trinh T Minh-Ha, Alex Potts, Carol Robertson, Lawrence Stone, Linda Williams. Respondents: Jane Flax, Sally McConnell-Ginet)
      - Arnold Davidson, Philosophy, University of Chicago. Lecture: "The Horror of Monsters" March 6, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Stone, Laurence, History, Princeton University. Lecture: "Sexuality in the West" March 20, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Laurence Stone, History, Princeton University. Lecture: "Harris vs. Lingaard, 1968" March 22, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Jeffrey Weeks, History and Sociology, Bristol Polytechnic University, UK. Lecture: "Invented Moralities" March 28, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Gwendolyn Wright, Architecture, Columbia University. Lecture: "Prescribing the Ideal Home" April 2, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Gwendolyn Wright, Architecture, Columbia University. Forum: "Discourse of Desire, Discourse of Mastery in French Colonial Urbanism" April 5, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Teresa De Lauretis, History of Consciousness, University of California at Santa Cruz. Lecture: "Freud, Sexuality, Perversion" April 8, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Craig Adcock. Science Associates Lecture: "Sexuality in the Art of Marcel DuChamp" April 9, 1991 (Box 3)
      - Teresa De Lauretis, History of Consciousness, University of California at Santa Cruz. Lecture: "Revisiting Female Homosexuality" April 19, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Judith Butler, Johns Hopkins University, untitled Undated (Box 4)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Catherine Mackinnon, Law, University of Michigan. Inaugural Lecture: "Does Sexuality Have a History?" September 12, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Jacques Revel. Brown Bag: "Foucault Among Historians: A Story of Uncertainty" October 23, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Conference: "Michel Foucault's History of Sexuality", November 2, 1990, 3 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      - Sylvia Hacker. Lecture November 13, 1990, 2 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      - Carol Armstrong, Art History, University of California at Berkeley. Forum: "Julia Margaret Cameron" November 26, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Louis Montrose, English, University of California at San Diego. Lecture: "The Work of Gender in the Discourse of Discovery" November 28, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Douglas Crimp, Sarah Lawrence. Interview with WUOM February 14, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Conference: "The Constructed Body" February 15-16, 1991, 8 audiocassettes (Box 4)
      - Arnold Davidson, Philosophy, University of Chicago. Lecture: "The Horror of Monsters" March 6, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Jeffrey Weeks, History and Sociology, Bristol Polytechnic University. Lecture: "Invented Moralities: Values in an Age of Uncertainty" March 28, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Gwendolyn Wright, Architecture, Columbia University. Lecture: "Prescribing the Ideal Home" April 2, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Teresa De Lauretis, History of Consciousness, University of California at Santa Cruz. Lecture: "Freud, Sexuality, Perversion" April 8, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Craig Adcock, Art and Art History, University of Notre Dame. Lecture: "James Rosenquist's F-111" April 10, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Panel: Resident Fellows reflect on their year at the Institute April 16, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Authority of the Past 1991-1992
    - Videotapes
      - Selma Jeanne Cohen, Editor The International Encyclopedia of Dance. Forum: "If We Can Find It, What Can We Do About It?", September 20, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Sidra DeKoven Ezrahi, Institute of Contemporary Jewry, Hebrew University of Jerusalem. Forum: "The Exiled Imagination" October 4, 1991 (Box 4)
      - David Bromwich, English, Yale University. Forum: "Liberal Learning and Group Thinking" November 22, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Conference: Religion and Authority February 6-February 8, 1992, 6 videotapes
        - Arnold Eisen, Religious Studies, Stanford. Conference session: "The Search for Authority in Twentieth-Century Judaic Studies" (Box 4)
        - Barbara Stoler Miller, Oriental Studies, Barnard, Columbia. Conference session: "The Authority of the Hindu Epics: Genealogy, Authenticity, and Authorship" (Box 4)
        - Garth Fowden, National Hellenic Research Foundation. Conference session: "Empire to Commonwealth: Consequences of Monotheism in Late Antiquity" (Box 4)
        - Bruce Kuklick, History, University of Pennsylvania. Conference session: "Puritans in Babylon: The Ancient Near East and the Revolution in Historical Thought" (Box 4)
        - Wendy Doniger, Divinity School, University of Chicago. Conference session: Respondent (Box 4)
        - Robert Sullivan, St. John's Seminary and Yvonne Haddad, History, University of Massachusetts. Conference sessions: "The Recovery of the Past: Current Paradigms for an Islamic Future;" "Modernizing Tradition: Some Catholic Neoscholastics and the Genealogy of Natural Rights" (Box 4)
      - Charles Rosen, Music and Social Thought, University of Chicago. Forum: "Second Editions: The Weight of the Past" February 14, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Caroline Humphrey, Anthropology, Cambridge University. Forum: "Rethinking Moral Authority in Post-Socialist Mongolia" March 20, 1992 (Box 5)
      - David Belin, Attorney, Des Moines, Iowa. Lecture: "Rewriting History: The Prostitution of the Assassination" March 24, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Richard Popkin, Philosophy (Emeritus), Washington University. Forum: "New Views about Skepticism in the Enlightenment" April 3, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Concert: Venus and Adonis April 24, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Cassette Tapes
      - Sidra Ezrahi, Institute of Contemporary Jewry, Hebrew University of Jerusalem. Lecture: "A Conversation in the Mountain" September 19, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Sarah Pomeroy, Classics, Hunter College and Graduate School of CUNY. Lecture: "Women, Humanism and the Deconomicus of Xenophor" October 10, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Thomas Gunning, Film, SUNY-Purchase and Gillian Anderson, Library of Congress. Panel: D.W. Griffith's 1916 film Intolerance, November 2, 1991 (Box 5)
      - David Bromwich, English, Yale University. Lecture: "Wollstonecroft as a Reader of Burke" November 18, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Kurt W. Forster, Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities. Lecture: "The Authority of the Past and the Author of the New in Karl F. Schinkel's Neo-Classical Architecture" December 5, 1991 (Box 5)
      - David Keightley, Chinese Studies, University of California at Berkeley. Lecture: [reflection on how the successors to two traditions, Chinese and Western, learn what it is to be human] December 12, 1991 (Box 5)
      - Conference: Religion and Authority February 6-February 8, 1992, 6 audiocassettes
        - Arnold Eisen, Religious Studies, Stanford. Conference session: "The Search for Authority in Twentieth-Century Judaic Studies" (Box 5)
        - Barbara Stoler Miller, Oriental Studies, Barnard, Columbia. Conference session: "The Authority of the Hindu Epics: Genealogy, Authenticity, and Authorship" (Box 5)
        - Garth Fowden, National Hellenic Research Foundation. Conference session: "Empire to Commonwealth: Consequences of Monotheism in Late Antiquity" (Box 5)
        - Bruce Kuklick, History, University of Pennsylvania. Conference session: "Puritans in Babylon: The Ancient Near East and the Revolution in Historical Thought" (Box 5)
        - Robert Sullivan, Church History, St. John's Seminary. "Modernizing Tradition: Some Catholic Neoscholastics and the Genealogy of Natural Rights" (Box 5)
        - Yvonne Haddad, History, University of Massachusetts, "The Recovery of the Past: Current Paradigms for an Islamic Future" (Box 5)
      - David Belin, Attorney, Des Moines. Lecture: "Rewriting History: The Prostitution of the Assassination" March 24, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Anthony Pinnock and David Roblou, Early English Opera Society. Interview. WUOM April 23, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Humanities Camp May 15-17, 1992
        - "Opera as Theater", 7 audiocassettes (Box 5)
  - Utopian Visions 1992-1993
    - Videotapes
      - Jonathan Beecher, Forum: "Two Concepts of Utopia" September 11, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Lemuel Johnson, English, University of Michigan. Forum: "Can the Ethiopian Change His Color? Colonial Education and the Utopian Gesture" October 16, 1992 (Box 5)
      - Conference: "Utopian Revisions: Nationalism and Civil Society in Eastern Europe" October 29-30, 1992, 6 videotapes
        - Richard Wagner, writer, Berlin; writer in residence, Oberlin College. Conference session: "Ethnic Minorities in the National State: The Case of German-Romanians" (Box 5)